דף Daf is ע"ה Ayin He 75, we started at the bottom
of ע"ד עמוד ב'. Ayin Dalet Amud Bet. We are talking about
this sheep or cow that's found in the mother's stomach when you
שחט shecht the mother. We were introduced to the fact that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir actually says that it is not made permissible through
the שחיטה shechita of the mother, but the position of the Rabbis
which is the dominant one that we've been dealing with since the
beginning says it is. And then the גמרא Gemara says, well how
much do we really consider it meat? While interestingly on the one
hand for the purposes of not only the שחיטה, shechita, but the
גמרא Gemara said even the fat and the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh,
it's not its own animal, it's like a limb, so there's no
prohibition of fat and גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, but even as a
limb there's a prohibition of blood. But then the other thing the
גמרא Gemara said is that's only for areas relating to food. For
other areas like plowing with a donkey and so on, or even
potentially redeeming it for a donkey for a firstborn donkey, it is
considered like a animal and if it's alive and so on and
now it's grown up and it is not considered like food. So
the issue about redeeming was a question about the link to קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. So now we continue with that larger theme. Let's
take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara picks up the following:
מהו למנות, mahu limnos, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 lines down
in the wide lines on ע"ד עמוד ב'. Ayin Dalet Amud Bet.
מהו למנות בו ראשון ראשוני? mahu limnos bo rishon rishoni? So you've
got the mother, you שחט shechted the mother, you've got the mother,
you've got the fetus. Are they now that now that it's שחט
shechted and dead and so on, are they now considered two objects
or one object? For what purpose? Let's say the mother becomes טמא,
tamei, some טמא tamei thing, a carcass such as it, a נבילה.
neveilah. The mother is a ראשון, rishon, first degree derivative. What is
the status with the fetus? Is the fetus considered to be a
part of the mother so it gets טומאה tumei directly, right? If
you touch a dead carcass, a fetus or whatever, or a dead
corpse, you know, a human corpse to the head of a dead
of a cow, of a כשר kosher שחט shechted cow which isn't
itself טמא, tamei, right? So which part becomes טמא? tamei? The head
or everything? So of course everything, right? The head, the body, the
feet. You don't say the head is a ראשון, rishon, the body
is a שני, sheini, by the time you get to the tail
it's a שלישי. shelishi. No, it's all one object, it touched the
dead thing, it's all a ראשון. rishon. Well what happens if in
that mother that was שחט shechted is a dead fetus? And the
mother touched the, you know, touched something טמא. tamei. The mother, the
entire body of the mother is a ראשון. rishon. What about the
fetus? Is that also a ראשון rishon or is that a שני?
sheini? Right? The שחיטה shechita of the mother worked for the fetus,
but is the fetus considered how much is it considered one body
with the mother? And this is a question that in different ways
we've been asking from the very beginning. Do we say it is
literally part of the body as much as anything else? Do we
say no, no, no, it's dependent, it's connected, it's not part of
the body? Okay that was the question, for example if you dismembered
the fetus it wasn't in the mother's womb, it wasn't as bad
as cutting off an organ. Okay, so here the question is on
the, you know, that similar question. Is it considered one unit that
it's all one or two, conducts טומאה tuma as one, or are
they stages? Yes.
This only is a question if the mother is dead.
If the mother is dead, and then it's meat, and also that
the fetus is dead. Okay at least we will assume for now
that if the fetus were alive, even though it was considered שחט,
shechted, it can't become טמא tamei as alive. Number one, just because
the whole concept of טומאה tumah relates to foodstuff, so even though
it might not require שחיטה, shechita, it doesn't mean it's fit to
be eaten as an animal that's still alive. And number two, you
know, as we said before it's for purposes of eating which presumably
meant כשרות, kashrus, not is the fetus already considered שחט? shechted? Whereas
now it's an issue of טומאה. tumah. So there's טומאה, tumah, one
of the ideas of טומאה tumah is it's considered food, but nevertheless
presumably we're talking yes, that not only is the mother שחט, shechted,
the fetus is שחט, shechted, but we want to know are they
one item or two items? Yes.
Would it be the same thing if it swallowed a dead שרץ
sheretz or something depending on how digested it was? What? Would it
be the same thing if it swallowed a, let's forget about if
it was pregnant or not. A cow swallowed a dead שרץ, sheretz,
let's say, whatever, and then, you know, depending on how digested it
was would you have the same question?
Depending on how digested,
you mean I guess if it's digested it's part of the mother's
body and then there's nothing to talk about, but like, you know,
swallowed a whatever.
But there's no טומאה tumah through swallowing, טומאה tumah only comes through
touching. And anyway live things aren't טמא. tamei.
No I said it swallowed dead שרץ. sheretz.
If it swallowed a dead שרץ, sheretz, who cares? If the animal
is alive the animal can't become טמא. tamei.
Right no, then you שחט shechted it and then, you know...
No, no, no, once it's inside the body that gets to טומאה
tumah and all those other things. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Now we would think that the issue as
I said, just to qualify, I said that presumably we're talking about
the fetus is dead as well, but that's not going to be
so clear for all the reasons I said, but that's not going
to be so clear from the perspective of the גמרא. Gemara. So
let's take a look. רבי יוחנן אמר מונין בו ראשון ושני, Rabbi
Yochanan amar monin bo rishon v'sheini, the fetus is separate and the
mother becomes טמא, tamei, the mother's a ראשון, rishon, the fetus is
a
שני. sheini. וריש לקיש אמר אין מונין בו ראשון ושני, v'Reish Lakish
amar ein monin bo rishon v'sheini, no you do not go down,
you do not go ראשון שני, rishon sheini, you consider it all
one unit, it all becomes טמא tamei together. Says why? Now he
does not actually say it as extreme as I did, because as
I indicated we already have evidence... As indicated prior, that even though
the שחיטה sh'chita works, the fetus is not completely an integral unit
with the mother. So here's the way ריש לקיש Resh Lakish phrases
why you don't go down. נעשה כאגוז המתקשקש בקליפתה. na'aseh ke'egoz hamitkashkesh
bekliptah.
He says imagine you have a nut that you can is making
sound inside of its shell, right? There's like what would be an
example of that, like an almond but the shell was too tight.
A pecan or a walnut?
Okay, good, okay, well walnut though it's a little packed tight so
you don't really hear it bounce around. Is there something else you
can sort of shake the shell?
Acorns or hazelnuts.
Acorns, okay, or or a pistachio or any whatever. So imagine you
have that, okay, so imagine you have that, and you are מטמא
metamei something טמא tamei touches the shell, right? You don't say oh
it touched the shell the shell is a ראשון, rishon, the shell
is now touching the thing inside of it it's a שני. sheni.
What you actually say is that the shell is considered not one
unit with the nut inside, but a protector of the nut inside.
It surrounds it, it wraps it, it protects it, and this is
a principle we have by טומאה tumah of שומר shomer or יד,
yad, things that are extensions or protectors, that is considered to be,
it's enough of a protector and extension that the טומאה tumah that
touches the shell, it's considered as if it touched the thing on
the inside. So you don't have to call it one unit to
say that it's מטמא metamei the other thing directly. So says ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish the same is true for the fetus inside the
mother. I'll concede that it's not one unit. There as we said
there are other indications that it's not literally one unit, but nevertheless
the mother's womb and body is a protector for the fetus. So
if the mother is טמאה, tmeiah, it's no worse than the shell
of the nut that therefore it directly is מטמא metamei the fetus.
Okay that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says. Seems to make a
lot of sense. Let's take a look. So, איתיביה רבי שמעון בן
לקיש לרבי יוחנן. Etivei Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish asks רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. הבשר מגע נבילה דברי רבי
מאיר. Ha'basar maga neveilah de'ivrei Rabbi Meir.
Going back to that fun case somewhere we won't be on it
too long, of when the limb is sticking out of the womb,
the fetus, and the question is what's the status of the limb?
And when you שוחט shochet the mother. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says the limb is a נבילה, neveilah, and the fetus which is
connected to the limb is something that touched a נבילה. neveilah. וחכמים
אומרים מגע טריפה שחוטה. V'chachamim omrim maga treifah sh'chutah. And we know
the rabbis say the limb is just like it's a טריפה treifah
fine. We're going to focus on רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. בשלמא לדידי
דאמינא חד גופא. Bishlama l'didi d'amina chad gufa. Says ריש לקיש, Resh
Lakish,
it works well for me that I consider the mother and the
fetus one unit, okay, although we just said before not literally one
unit too. איכשור בדמא דאמיה. Ichshur b'dama d'imei. So now we have
a question. How is it that the limb made the fetus טמא?
tamei? The fetus, it's true, was שוחט, shocheted, the mother it's considered
to be food, but even food needs what הכשר, hechsher, needs to
come in contact with liquid to be susceptible for טומאה. tumah. So
how is it that that happens for the fetus? The only way
it happens is, what happens when you שוחט shochet the mother? Blood
comes out of the mother, the blood touches the mother's skin, and
that is makes the mother susceptible for טומאה. tumah. So it would
only, it only can apply to the fetus if you consider the
mother and the fetus for purposes of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah essentially
to be one unit. Okay, so for example let's take the case
of the nut, as an interesting example. You have a nut, you
picked it off of a tree, right? The nut never came in
contact with water, but the shell did. Would the shell coming in
contact with water mean enough that you can now touch the shell
and make the nut טמא? tamei? So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is
saying that's how this is working here, and that's why the fetus
can become טמא. tamei. That works for me.
אלא לדידך במאי איכשור. Ella l'didach b'mai ichshur. According to you, what
made the fetus susceptible? It didn't come in contact with liquid, and
you consider it a separate thing. אמר ליה בשחיטה כרבי שמעון. Amar
lei bi'shchita k'Rabbi Shimon. Through שחיטה sh'chita and like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. You will remember way back when we had when we were
still talking about שחיטה, sh'chita, right? When we said that there was
a position that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said if you שוחט shochet
an animal even if somehow miraculously no blood came out, the act
of שחיטה sh'chita which converted the animal into food, that substituted for
הכשר hechsher and you don't need meat to come in contact with
water because the act of שחיטה sh'chita makes it susceptible. So he
said forget the blood. You did a שחיטה, sh'chita, it worked on
the mother, it worked on the fetus, and that's why the fetus
is susceptible. It does not prove one unit or two units. איתיביה
רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Etivei Rabbi Yochanan l'Resh Lakish. So now רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asks ריש לקיש Resh Lakish from a ברייתא baraita
that is more directly on this point. עברה בנהר, Avar b'nahar, this
cow that is pregnant and's got a fetus in its womb goes
in a river and it comes in contact with liquid. הוכשר, Huchshar,
then it became, wait, I did not explain the case right. You
שוחט shocheted the mother, you had a living fetus, and now it
doesn't require שחיטה sh'chita and now it's grown up and it's a
few years old, this fetus that now doesn't require שחיטה sh'chita and
now it is walking through a river and comes in contact with
water. Okay? Because remember the idea of needing to come in contact
with a liquid is only once the thing has already become food.
So now again we're going to revisit this case about this fetus
that doesn't need שחיטה, sh'chita, is it already considered food or not?
Can it become טמא tamei as a live animal? Right? So that's
a question. Let's take a look. So this thing that now has
grown up and doesn't require שחיטה sh'chita walked through a river, הוכשר,
huchshar, it became susceptible. הלך לבית הקברות, halach l'beit hakvarot, it went
into a cemetery, נטמא, nitma, it becomes טמא. tamei. So here's an
amazing idea that the fetus even as a live animal can become
טמא. tamei. As I said, it's quite bizarre because it's not really
like טומאה tumah requires that it be food. A food or a
vessel. Do you call it food already? Presumably yes, it doesn't require
שחיטה, shechita, you call it food. Okay, so that the thing becomes
טמא tamei even live. But what do you see? He says, he
says, look, this proves the opposite of you. According to you, why
would it have to have passed through a river? Why didn't it
become הוכשר huchshar through the blood of the mother? So you see
that it was not considered to be one with the mother.
בשלמא לדידי, bishlama l'didi, it works according to me, דאמינא תרי גופי
נינהו, d'amina t'rei gufay ninhu, they're two bodies, משום הכי הוכשר, mishum
hachi huchshar, that's why it became susceptible, אם im עבדה, abda, if
it became susceptible, yes, then it becomes טמא, tamei, לא הוכשר לא,
lo huchshar lo, if it didn't pass through the river, no. אלא
לדידך, ela l'didach, according to you, דאמרת חד גופא הוא, d'amart chad
gufa hu, it's all one body, so at least for טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah purposes,
הא דאיתכשר ha d'it-huchshar בדמא דאמיה, b'dama d'imei, it became susceptible through
the blood of the mother. Why does it have to go through
the river?
What is in the case where she shechted the mother?
If you didn't shecht the mother, then there wouldn't be any special
status.
No, let's say the mother died.
Then the fetus would be a נבילה, neveilah, it would be... would
require שחיטה, shechita, it couldn't be הוכשר huchshar as a live animal.
No, meaning is... wouldn't you say that... let's say regular case. The
mother died, and then the fetus inside... they extracted the fetus somehow.
Yeah, and you need
שחיטה, shechita, would it be a נבילה? neveilah?
No, according to anybody. No, it needs שחיטה, shechita, that's our משנה,
mishna, but it wouldn't be הוכשר huchshar as a live animal. So
the גמרא Gemara says, בשחיטה יבשתא ודלא כרבי שמעון. b'shechita yaveshta v'delo
k'rabbi Shimon. So we're talking again about one of these miraculous cases
where there was שחיטה shechita with no blood, and because there was
שחיטה shechita with no blood, therefore it did not become susceptible through
the blood of the mother, not like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the
שחיטה shechita itself did not make it susceptible, and that's why it
needed to pass through the river. But okay, it's hard enough to
imagine that that case could ever occur, let alone to assume that
that was taken for granted in this case of the ברייתא. braita.
So the simple sense of the ברייתא braita says two things: it
did not become הוכשר huchshar through the blood of the mother, it's
a separate unit, which makes sense based on other things that we've
seen, and number two, which is really shocking, which the גמרא Gemara
is now going to look at, is that even as a live
animal, even though before we said maybe for כשרות kashrus purposes the
שחיטה shechita worked and it's considered a limb, here we're saying even
for טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah and even as a live animal, it
can become טמא. tamei. Let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara
continues this. Top of ע"ה ע"א. ayin hey amud aleph. מאן תנא
עבר בנהר הוכשר הלך לבית הקברות נטמא? man tanna avar b'nahar huchshar
halach l'veit hakvarot nitma? Who is the תנא tanna that says if
it goes through the river, that's required and it becomes susceptible and
in the... and it goes to the cemetery it becomes טמא tamei
even as a live animal? אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, so
said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוסי הגלילי היא, Rabbi Yose HaGlili
hi, it's רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, and here the גמרא
Gemara is sensitive to the bizarre nature of a live animal becoming
טמא. tamei. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
mishum Rabbi Yose HaGlili, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
said in the name of רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, מטמא
טומאת אוכלין, metamei tumat ochlin, this live fetus that was... the mother
was shechted and it's live and now it's grown up and it's
a cow and it's been walking around, this live fetus, מטמא טומאת
אוכלין, metamei tumat ochlin, can become טמא tamei the טומאה tumah foodstuff,
it is considered food, we said yesterday for food purposes, yes we
assumed that meant for כשרות kashrus purposes, but now we're saying if
you consider it like a limb of the mother for food, so
it's food, food can become טמא tamei even as a live animal.
וצריך הכשר, v'tzarich hechshar, but it is true that it does need
to come into contact with a liquid. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, and
the sages say, אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, eino metamei tumat ochlin, even
if you say that it doesn't need שחיטה, shechita, there's no problem
with the חלב, chelev, no problem with the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh,
it does not become טמא, tamei, it's a living, breathing animal, מפני
שהוא חי, mipnei shehu chai, because it is living. וכל שהוא חי,
v'chol shehu chai, אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, eino metamei tumat ochlin, anything
that's living doesn't become טמא, tamei, so you can say for כשרות
kashrus purposes we're not going to treat it as its own animal,
for כשרות kashrus purposes we will have seen that its כשרות kashrus
status, its identity in the world of כשרות, kashrus, was defined when
the mother was shechted and there it was a part of the
mother, so it doesn't require שחיטה, shechita, its חלב chelev isn't special
חלב, chelev, its גיד הנשה gid hanasheh isn't a גיד הנשה, gid
hanasheh, it's always like a limb of the mother, that's כשרות. kashrus.
But here, with טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, you can't ignore the fact
that the animal is alive and breathing and living, like we said
yesterday for other things as well, so like plowing with a donkey
also, it's a live animal and you cannot treat it just as
food. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה,
v'azal Rabbi Yochanan l'taameih, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his
reasoning that identifies רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili with this idea that even as a live
thing it could be considered food and become טמא. tamei. And here
there actually is interestingly a... an interesting parallel, which is: so if
you were to think, 'Oh this is interesting, can something alive that
is fit to be eaten become טמא tamei as food?' Do we
have anything else in הלכה halacha that can be eaten when it
is still alive and we could ask if something that is both
alive but edible is considered food for טומאה וטהרה? tumah v'taharah? That's
the question here. This animal's alive, but in theory it's edible, it
doesn't require שחיטה. shechita. Do we have anything else like that that
doesn't need to be dead? Grasshoppers and fish, they don't need to
be dead. So let's take a look at where the גמרא Gemara
goes with it. Okay, very good, ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, v'azal Rabbi
Yochanan l'taameih, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his reasoning, דאמר
רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, as רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. רבי
יוסי הגלילי בית שמאי אמרו דבר אחד *Rabbi Yosei HaGelili Beit Shamai
amru davar echad*. רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosei HaGelili* and בית שמאי
*Beit Shamai* said the same thing. רבי יוסי הגלילי הא דאמרן *Rabbi
Yosei HaGelili ha de'amran*, רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosei HaGelili* that we
said, the animal could be alive and once it's considered food could
become טמא tamei. *tamei*, ובית שמאי *uBeit Shamai* and what did בית
שמאי *Beit Shamai* say? דתנן *detnan*, we taught in a משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* in עוקצין *Uktzin*, a מסכת *Masechet* we are not going to
get up to in our דף יומי *Daf Yomi*. It's all about
טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah? *tum'ah ve'taharah*. דגים מאימתי מקבלים טומאה tumah *Dagim
me'eimatai mekabelim tum'ah*, when can a fish become טמא tamei. *tamei* as
food? בית שמאי אומר משיצודו *Beit Shamai omer mishe'yitzadu*, from the very
moment they are caught in the net, meaning not if they're under
the ocean because you know, they're not food if they're swimming around
in the pond. They have to, in order to be food, they
have to somehow be, you know, under human control, right? They're sort
of under my, you know, so they're in. So once I've caught
them and you can now I'm controlling them and I could put
them on... Yeah. So if you've got a net in the water,
once they are seized by humans and they're edible in this state,
they're already considered food. Okay, so that's what בית שמאי *Beit Shamai*
says. What if you're capturing them because you want to sell them
to an aquarium? That I don't know. Okay, but at least in
the context that you're capturing them, you're capturing tuna or minnows or
whatever and you're pulling them up in your net or they're in
their net even in the water, right now, once they're caught they're
already food. Okay, I'll take your question in a second, let's see
what the debate is. בית הלל אומר משימותו *Beit Hillel omer mishe'yamutu*.
בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says I don't care that they, you don't
need שחיטה shechita *shechita*, something isn't food while it's alive. It has
to die before it can be food. Okay, so that's what בית
הלל *Beit Hillel* says and that's what we, the issue exactly about
the calf. It can be eaten but it's still alive. And now
we have an interesting position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר מששאין יכולין לחיות *Rabbi Akiva omer mishe'she'ein
yecholim lichyot*. It's sort of a compromised position. It has to be
that it can no longer live. You know, if it could be
that if you were to throw it back in the water, it
could then live, then it's not yet considered to be food. Who
knows what's going to happen to it? You'll put it in your
aquarium, you'll throw it back in the water. There is a concept
of being dead, but it doesn't have to literally die, and it
has to just be that it's going to die. Almost like a
טריפה treifa *treifa* idea. Okay, now again, maybe that's because he said
as long as it's not necessarily going to die, you could always
throw it back. Maybe that's the issue for him. Okay, so it
has to somewhat be this change of status, the way you're going
to use it has to be a little irrevocable. So it has
to be that it can no longer live. Okay, so says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, מאי בינייהו *mai beina'ihu*? What's between them? So between
who? רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva,
*Rabbi Akiva* and בית הלל *Beit Hillel*. What's a situation in which
it's not dead but it won't survive? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, דג מקרטע איכא
בינייהו *dag mikarteia ika beina'ihu*. A fish that is מקרטע *mikarteia*. Now
what does מקרטע *mikarteia* mean? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says מקרטע *mikarteia*
means, well תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says it means thrashing. רש"י *Rashi* also
says it means thrashing. Yes, but רש"י *Rashi* says it means that
it's thrashing around in its last throes of life, but it's still
alive because it's thrashing, but it already has dried up significant segments
that it can no longer revive. That's the way רש"י *Rashi* has
it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says you would not have to ask the
question what's between them, between the position that says dead and a
position that says can't survive. It's obvious what the difference is. An
animal that's still alive that's going to die. Okay, תוספות *Tosafot* says
the question is what's between
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* and בית שמאי *Beit Shamai*? What
is the
stage, says
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, hold on let me just check תוספות *Tosafot*
one minute.
Right, what is the stage where you say it's sort of asking
the same thing but on the flip? It's still alive, that we
get, but according to one it's going to die and according to
the next it's not yet... you know, what's the stage when you
say that it's already going to die, but coming not from the
dead end of the spectrum, the live end of the spectrum? So
תוספות *Tosafot* basically says the idea of thrashing as well, but thrashing
to make the other point. Not the point that it's about... it's
going to die but it's still in its last thrashes and its
last throes, but he sort of saying thrashing is בית שמאי *Beit
Shamai*'s point. Meaning if it's jumping up and down vigorously, you know,
then that shows that it's not even... then that's not still can
survive even if you were to put it back. Once it's no
longer vigorously thrashing, you know, then already that would be in the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* category. Either way, it's clear what
the difference is. One says as soon as it's caught, the other
says it's dead, and the other says only even if it's alive
it can be טמא tamei *tamei* but only if it's not going
to survive. And here you have again this fascinating question. It can
be eaten in its current state but it is alive. Okay, so
for בית הלל *Beit Hillel* that's no good, it's not food yet
and therefore this fetus that has survived and doesn't need שחיטה shechita
*shechita* would not be food and could not become טמא tamei, *tamei*.
For בית שמאי *Beit Shamai* it could, and again for רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva? *Rabbi Akiva* somewhat of a compromise position, presumably having to
do with how revocable or irrevocable it is. You had a question
Charlie?
Modern fish farms, the fish would spend its whole life never having
been not caught.
Right, so according to בית שמאי *Beit Shamai* and that's exactly the
thing, you're growing it as food and it's always under your control
so it's always food. Right, yep. And biology is actually...
when did they eat fish in this state? Still alive?
I doubt it. I don't know we I can't think of any
time the גמרא Gemara ever records that. I mean, this does seem
to be, you know, hypothetical, that questioned that since it's possible to
be eaten it becomes טמא. tamei, I can't think of any times
or any case where the גמרא Gemara, talks about them eating fish
while it's still that fresh. But somebody did point out the new
fancy thing with sushi is as if raw fish weren't enough, you
know, there's something where there's now a whole delicacy of eating live
fish. Eating them where they're still so you can feel them like
squiggling down your throat. Like goldfish
eating?
Like goldfish eating rituals or there you go.
And goldfish are kosher, they're a type of a carp I believe.
Yeah, that's right.
So there you
go.
Okay. What? I'm talking about the מפרפר, mefarper, I still remember like
a very early on our marriage when Devora and I took one
of the—we didn't have kids yet, so we actually could take a
vacation. And we went, you know, somewhere like I forget in New
England, and we went boating, we went fishing, I think it was
the first time Devora went fishing and she actually caught a fish,
you know, she pulled it up, a nice-sized fish into the boat.
And there it was, it was like flopping around, you know, in
the boat, and she was like, she didn't know what to do,
ah! So I just took the oar and I beat it into
submission because, you know, you gotta do that. I know. But anyway,
that's a מפרפר, mefarper, okay? And it is quite fascinating, fish really,
you know, significantly after they're caught if you throw them back they
can they can survive. All right, anyway. So the גמרא Gemara goes
on. Okay, let's take a look. בעי רב חסדא, Ba'ei Rav Chisda,
Rav Chisda asked. נולדו בדגים סימני טרפה מהו. Noldu bedagim simanei treifa
mahu. Ha!
So since we're talking about fish whether they can survive or not,
a question we've never had before. We've had a whole פרק perek
of discussing whether a cow and a sheep can survive, but now
we're talking about if a fish can survive according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva to know whether it can become טמא. Now we can
talk about טרפות treifos by fish. Okay? Because now it matters. If
a טרפה treifa can't survive, so according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that would be the dividing line between whether it could become טמא
or not. So you have a fish that is a טרפה. treifa.
What is the story? Let's find out how—well, no, we're not going
to go into details. Let's take a look. תיבעי למאן דאמר טרפה
חיה, Tiba'ei leman d'amar treifa chaya, you can ask it according to
the position that a טרפה treifa can survive. Okay, why, why should
it matter? We'll see. ותיבעי למאן דאמר טרפה אינה חיה, Vetiba'ei leman
d'amar treifa einah chaya, and certainly the question is relevant according to
the position that a טרפה treifa cannot survive. So let's take a
look. תיבעי למאן דאמר טרפה חיה, Tiba'ei leman d'amar treifa chaya, you
can ask according to the position a טרפה treifa will survive. So
why should it then even be at all relevant in the case
of the fish? Because I could say like this, בהמה הוא דנפיש
חיותא. beheima hu denafish chayusa.
Maybe when this type of a problem, whatever it is, a hole
in the lung or whatever—fish don't have lungs. And what do fish
have that animals don't?
Gills, I thought they had gills.
Gills. Those are lungs?
Well, I'm sorry, there's some fish that have lungs.
Oh, okay. Lungfish. Lungfish. Anyway, whatever it's got, it has a little
heart. Okay, a hole in the heart. Okay, anyway, the fact that
that might not be a—that might not make the animal die if
it's a cow, that's because דנפיש חיותא, denafish chayusa, because its life
force is great, meaning it's a big living thing, so maybe a
little injury it can survive, a little hole. אבל דגים דלא נפיש
חיותא, aval dagim dela nafish chayusa, but fish that don't have a
powerful life force, so לא, lo, maybe therefore maybe a similar type
of an injury means that they won't survive. Now, I want to
point out that even if it's true that, you know, somehow a
similar injury by a fish will be more dangerous, still, the גמרא,
Gemara it's still interesting that the גמרא Gemara asks the question about
a טרפה, treifa, because if you're of the position that a טרפה
treifa can live, then what's special about the—about what's on the list
of טרפות? treifos? Those don't mean that it'll die. So maybe other
injuries also will be relevant for a fish, and maybe not all
of these injuries, you know, if the list is completely arbitrary, even
if a fish is more, what's the word, like susceptible, you know,
less healthy, as it were, you know,
impervious, why specifically the list of טרפות treifos if a טרפה, treifa,
if a טרפה treifa can live? So this suggests, and we never
really sort of elaborated on this when we learned טרפות treifos because
the dominant position was טרפה אינה חיה, treifa einah chaya, it suggests
that even the position טרפה חיה treifa chaya admits that these types
of injuries most likely cause death, or in many cases, or have
the potential, it's just saying it won't necessarily happen. Okay, which also
explains as we were discussing, if you say that a טרפה treifa
can survive, then what basis do you use to determine other than
הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, but there were a lot of
discussions in the גמרא, Gemara so what basis can you determine if
something is on the list or off the list? So this makes
it suggest that even if a טרפה treifa can survive, that might
be somewhat of an exception or not so common, and that the
list is still compiled primarily based on things that are most likely
to or, you know, have a high potential in bringing about death.
And therefore we say even if by animals, cows and sheep, it
won't necessarily do it, maybe by fish it will necessarily do it.
That's according to the person that—the position that a טרפה treifa can
live. או
דלמא, O dilma, or do we say, אפילו למאן דאמר טרפה אינה
חיה, afilu leman d'amar treifa einah chaya, even according to the position
that a טרפה treifa cannot live, maybe it shouldn't be relevant by
fish. Why not? הני מילי בהמה דיש במינה שחיטה, Hani mili beheima
de-yesh bemina shechita, because then maybe טריפה treifa is only a relevant
concept by a cow or sheep or בהמה beheima where you need
שחיטה shechita, and טריפה treifa. says the שחיטה shechita doesn't work. So
there's a הלכה halacha of טריפה. treifa טריפה treifa. makes it
non-kosher. אבל בדגים דאין במינם שחיטה, Aval b'dagim de-ein beminam shechita, but
fish that don't have a concept of שחיטה, shechita, maybe there's not.
No, there's no concept of טריפה. treifa תיקו, Teiku, so it's unanswered.
So here's also what the heck is the גמרא Gemara talking about?
I understand that there's no halachic significance to טריפה treifa by fish.
But according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva. I'm asking a simple medical
fact. Is this fish going to survive or not? And if you
tell me that things with a טריפה treifa injury won't survive, then
that should be relevant. Who cares if the concept of טריפה treifa
is not relevant by fish? So here it seems that we're sort
of saying a little bit the opposite. We're saying that it's true
a טריפה treifa might cause death, but that's eventually cause death. Right?
So that might cause death 11 months from now. So when I
want to say according to רבי עקיבא, since this fish won't survive,
it's like it's already dead and it's like it's food, it might
not be enough to use the standard of טריפה treifa to say
it will die within the year. I don't care if it'll die
within the year. I'll worry about that a year from now. Right
now, it's nice and alive and healthy and I can't call it
food. So that's what it's saying. Maybe according to maybe the idea
that it'll die within a year is a relevant concept where טריפה
treifa, is a halachic concept. But for רבי עקיבא to say the
fish is like it's dead now and it's like food and could
become טמא, maybe it has to sort of its death has to
be a little bit more imminent. Okay, so leaves that as an
unanswered question, but clearly this gave the גמרא Gemara a nice fun
opportunity to talk about טריפות treifas by fish, which otherwise would never
have come up.
Okay, so now what do we hold? In what?
The טריפות treifas of רבי עקיבא? Yeah. How do you know? When
have you פסקנ'ד paskened טומאה וטהרה? tumah ve-taharah? Right.
But the case of the טריפה, treifa right, then can you eat
it?
No, we're not suggesting it affects the כשרות. kashrus. Purely a question
within רבי עקיבא of when can it become טמא, given that רבי
עקיבא said the standard is when it will no longer survive.
So you're saying that we don't really worry about eating it. It
could be a טריפה treifa and you could eat it for רבי
עקיבא.
Right, that's what I'm saying. There's no halachic concept of טריפה treifa.
from a כשרות kashrus perspective. Is it a relevant factor to consider
whether this fish can survive for laws of טומאה tuma. וטהרה? Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues, let's take a
look. Okay, תיקו, Teiku, we don't know. הטילה נפל, Hetila nefel, now
what happens if now we get into, again, another discussion about fetuses
which I think should be, at least seems to be very relevant
to the
again, the abortion type of a question, you'll see in a minute.
But it's not, I mean people don't bring it in. Okay, so
here is the cow miscarries. And now we want to know what
is the status, simple miscarriage, no בן פקועה, ben pakua, nothing like
that, simple miscarriage. Now you've got in front of you a stillbirth,
you know, like a cow that came out of the womb, a
fetus, it's pretty developed and it's dead. And we have the following
question. Is the fat, or you could say the גיד הנשה, gid
hanasheh, but we'll say the חלב, cheilev, in this fetus considered forbidden
fat or not? How do you treat, right, this dead fetus? I'll
give you a similar example. Remember we said for in the case
of humans
that if a baby once it's developed to the point that the
head is the size of a thimble, whatever that size is, that
if the baby dies and is born stillborn, it actually causes טומאה
of a corpse. Okay, so it's actually considered to have been a
human corpse. Again, you would think that would be relevant for the
abortion question, but whatever. So here, when this fetus comes out, is
this considered just to be a discharge or is this considered to
be a dead calf or dead sheep? If it's a dead calf
or dead sheep, so therefore the חלב cheilev is forbidden חלב, cheilev,
right? If it's just a discharge, then the חלב cheilev is nothing.
Isn't the whole thing forbidden?
What? Oh, you mean as a נבילה? neveilah? Right. Why don't we
ask the question about whether the stuff is actually a נבילה neveilah
or not? So I think that the גמרא Gemara is
that's a good
question.
It's a more serious penalty חלב cheilev than a נבילה. neveilah.
That is true, that is true. But the גמרא Gemara never goes
to actually the way the גמרא Gemara frames it, I may be
made it too much of an extreme as we'll see. The גמרא
Gemara never really frames it that it's just completely a discharge. The
גמרא Gemara basically says maybe it's not yet at a stage where
you can call it a בהמה. beheima. It's some type of an
animal, so maybe it's clear it's taken for granted it will be
a נבילה, neveilah, you have you know dead meat here or whatever,
but it or you know maybe who knows maybe it's בשר מן
החי basar min hachay because the mother's alive and it's some type
of flesh that came from the mother. So it never suggests that
it should be totally permissible to eat it. But to what degree
do you give it a future identity as its own type of
a בהמה. beheima. Okay, and so let's see the way the גמרא
Gemara, frames this. Let's take a look. Okay, הטילה נפל, Hetila nefel,
it miscarried a fetus. רבי יוחנן אמר חלבו כחלב בהמה, Rabbi Yochanan
amar chelbo ke-cheilev beheima, and this so now it's like you've got
a dead cow in front of you and the fat is like
the fat of a בהמה beheima and it's forbidden. רבי שמעון בן
לקיש אמר Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish amar ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
חלבו כחלב חיה. chelbo ke-cheilev chayah. No, it's not a בהמה, beheima,
it's not fully developed and born, it's a miscarriage and therefore why...
it might be forbidden meat for the reasons we said, נבילה, neveila,
בשר מן החי, basar min hachai, whatever, it's not yet a בהמה
beheima and therefore its fat is not forbidden. Now, by the way,
they both agree that if you שחט shecht the mother and it's
in the mother, it's okay. That clearly has the status of a
limb of the mother. But here, it actually came out. What's its
status? רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, חלבו כחלב בהמה. chelvo k'chelev
beheima. אווירא גרים, Avira garam, the air
causes, air meaning it's being born, it's coming out of the womb.
As soon as it comes out of the womb, right, then it
gets its own status and it's like its own בהמה. beheima. ריש
לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, חלבו כחלב חיה, chelvo k'chelev chayah, it's
not yet considered a בהמה. beheima. Why? חודשים גרמו, Chadashim garmu, it's
not enough that it's born, it has to be developed. Now you
can see why this sounds a little bit like, right, the abortion
question. When does it become a life? When it's born, or when
it's developing in the womb? Right? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says,
only when it's born—not only, because he's here acts to say when
it's born, that's sufficient. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying being born
is not sufficient, it needs to be fully developed, right, in order
to be in order to be its own life and its own
בהמה. beheima. חודשים גרמו. Chadashim garmu. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say,
כל היכא דלא כלו לו חודשיו, kol hicha d'lo chalu lo chodshav,
if it's not fully developed, לאו כלום הוא, lav klum hu, everybody
agrees it's nothing. You can't call it a בהמה beheima if it
is not fully developed and has not ended its gestation. Okay, so
if that's true, what's the debate going to be? כי פליגי היכא,
Ki pligi hicha, a case—remember we had the case the other day
about sticking your hand in the womb and שחטing shecht the animal
in the womb? We're going to have a similar case like this.
דהושיט ידו למעי בהמה, d'hoshit yado l'mei beheima, you stuck your hand
into the womb of the mother, וטלש חלב של בן תשעה חי,
v'talash chelev shel ben tish'ah chai, and there was in there a
fetus and you somehow tore open the fetus in the mother's womb
and pulled out the fat from the fetus in the mother's womb.
Okay, so it's a little crazy, but it's a thought experiment. And
the basic thought experiment is—and this really seems to be the abortion
question—you have a fully developed fetus in the mother's womb. At what
is it considered yet a בהמה beheima as long as it hasn't
been born? It hasn't been born, so it's in the mother's womb.
So we know if you שחט shecht the mother, it's considered to
have been שחטed shecht and a part of the mother. But you
didn't שחט shecht the mother. Okay, the mother's alive. And you didn't—right,
you have a fully developed fetus that hasn't been born. Okay, is
it considered to be have its own life and and therefore its
חלב chelev is forbidden, or at this stage, since it hasn't been
born, it's still just a part of the mother? All right, so
let's take a look. ואכלו, v'achlo, you eat it. So רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, חלבו כחלב בהמה. chelvo k'chelev beheima.
This fat, even while it has not yet been born, is like
the fat of a בהמה. beheima. Why? And not because of the
mother's fat. It's not the mother's fat, and that's clear, because if
you שחט shecht the mother, the fat is permitted. As its own
fat, it is forbidden, it is its own entity. חודשים גרמו, Chadashim
garmu, as long as it has the months, as long as it's
fully gestated, it's its own
entity. ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, חלבו כחלב חיה. chelvo k'chelev
chayah. No,
at this stage it's not yet a בהמה. beheima. Even if you
haven't שחטed shecht the mother, it's not yet a בהמה. beheima. חודשים
ואווירא גרמו. Chadashim v'avira garmu. You need things to not only reach
full gestation, you need them to be born before they have their
own identity. Okay, although however interestingly because obviously most of the abortion
questions are, you know, 99 percent of the abortion questions are before
the fetus has finished gestating. Right? And there the גמרא Gemara says
that before the gestation is finished, everybody agrees it's not yet a
בהמה. beheima. Okay, so again, fascinating to think about what parallels this
suggests for those questions. Okay, so that's the
debate. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitivei Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. Rabbi
Yochanan challenged Reish Lakish. So Rabbi Yochanan says it's just about the
gestation, not about being born. מה חלב שתי כליות האמור באשם מוצא
מכלל שליל. Ma chelev shtei klayot ha'amur b'asham mutza miklal shalil. So
this is a quote from תורת כהנים, Torat Kohanim, the ספרא, Sifra,
the rabbinic teaching on ויקרא. Vayikra. And it's proving this idea that
the fat of a fetus is not forbidden to be eaten, what
we've been sort of assuming all along, certainly when you שחט shecht
the mother. And not only that, if it's a קרבן, korban, it's
not fat that goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. The fat—these are these
are connected concepts. The only fat that goes on the מזבח mizbeach
is certain fat from the mother, not things that are in the
fetus. Okay. Now, one of the ways it proves it is it
says is, you know, sort of says a question, well, maybe it
only has, maybe it doesn't, maybe it's not forbidden to be eat,
but maybe you should still put it on the מזבח? mizbeach? How
do you know to exclude it completely? And it says because the
תורה Torah itself speaks about the fat not only of a שלמים,
shelamim, which can be a female and can have the fetus, but
even speaks about putting up the fat of an אשם, asham, which
can only be a זכר, zachar, a male animal. And therefore, in
that case, you'll never have fat of a fetus. So so that
is teaching you, the fact that it sort of repeats this concept
by a fetus—by an אשם, asham, and maybe you could have learned
it out from a שלמים, shelamim, it's repeating it to teach you
fat of a fetus is never relevant. It will never be put
on the מזבח, mizbeach, it is never forbidden, the same way you
never have it even that case by the case of an אשם,
asham, which is male. So let's take a look. Okay. מה... Ma...
מה חלב ושתי כליות האמור באשם, mah cheilev ushtei kelayot hamur baasham,
what's this story about the fat and the kidneys by the אשם,
asham, which is a male animal? מוצא מכללו של עובר mutsa miklalo
shel ubar is completely excluded from the case of a fetus. It's
male; it doesn't have fetuses. אף כל, af kol, even by female
animals, מוצא מכללו של עובר, mutsa miklalo shel ubar, the fetus is
completely excluded. You will never offer up the fat of a fetus.
You will never eat the—there's no problem eating the fat of the
fetus. Okay, now the question is in what case? Fat of the
fetus when you שחט shecht the mother, which is actually the קרבן
korban case? That we already know it's okay. Or the case Reish
Lakish and Rabbi Yochanan talking about, fat of the fetus even in
theory if you were to grab it while it's still in the
womb. So let's take a
look.
Oh, you see the fetus inside.
Yeah, it's a thought experiment. Okay. Or maybe what? Micro-surgery. Exactly. Look
at that, the Gemara anticipated that. Okay, so the Gemara says like
this: בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi,
according to me says Rabbi Yochanan, it makes sense that I say
the fat is forbidden in the mother's womb,
while the fetus is in the mother's womb. היינו דאיצטריך קרא למיעוטי.
haynu deitstritch kra lemayutei.
Therefore it has to say that even though there are ways in
which this fat on the fetus while it's in the mother's womb
could be forbidden if you were to stick your hand in and
grab it, nevertheless, once you שחט shecht the mother, it's not a
problem. Or nevertheless, don't bring it on the altar. But at least
it was a consideration because there were cases where that fat of
the fetus could be forbidden. אלא לדידך, ela ledidach,
but according to you, אמאי איצטריך? amai itstritch? Why do you need
a verse to exclude the fat of the fetus according to you?
It's never forbidden, even if you were to grab, stick your hand
inside. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he says back to him, היי
טעמא דידי נמי הכא. hai teima didi nami hacha. That's exactly where
I learn out my principle from. Meaning this is always like a
little question, right? If the Gemara proves something, I might have thought
X, the verse teaches Y. So does that mean that you keep
your initial assumption, or does the whole point of what the verse
teaches you to tell your whole assumption was wrong? So Reish Lakish
is saying that's exactly what I'm reading it. I might have thought
like you, Rabbi Yochanan, that the fat had some status while it
was still the fetus was still in the mother's womb. And the
fact that the verse teaches me you can eat it and don't
bring it as a sacrifice is telling me that the fat has
no status even if you don't שחט shecht the mother. That's exactly
what it's teaching me. Okay.
ואיכא דאמרי, veika deamri, some say איתיבי eitiv Reish Lakish to Rabbi
Yochanan that it was the reverse. Reish Lakish tried to prove his
case exactly from this ברייתא. braita. מה חלב ושתי כליות האמור באשם
מוצא מכללו של עובר, mah cheilev ushtei kelayot hamur baasham mutsa miklalo
shel ubar, the same way an אשם asham doesn't have a fetus,
so there's not going to be no fat from the fetus in
that case. אף כל מוצא מכללו של עובר, af kol mutsa miklalo
shel ubar, even in all cases, no fat from the fetus will
ever get put on the altar and be forbidden to eat. So
בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi, I understand according to me, משום הכי מיעטיה
רחמנא, mishum hachi miatyei rachmana, that's why the Torah had to exclude
it because there are cases where that fat is significant, where it's
forbidden fat if you were to take it from the fetus while
the fetus was still alive
from the womb. אלא לדידך, ela ledidach, according to you, ואיקרי? veikrei?
Why not offer that fat up on the altar? According to you
that you say that that fat
is—no, I said it wrong. Reish Lakish says for me the fat
never had—did I say it wrong? I don't know. Reish Lakish says
for me that fat never has significance. Since it has never had
significance, I understand why it's not offered and why it's not forbidden.
But according to you, Rabbi Yochanan, that you say that when the
fetus is in the womb, the fat is forbidden, so why not,
if it's really has status of fat, why not put it on
the altar? אמר ליה, amar lei, מידי דהוה אמחוסר זמן. midi dhavu
amechussar zman.
No, it's no different than an animal that was born that isn't
eight days
old. So it might have significance in theory, but it doesn't—it's not
yet, we will sell no wine before its time. So we'll offer
no fat before its time, and therefore as a fetus phase, it's
not yet fit. Now, it was a strange answer because remember, both
Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish agree that when you שחט shecht the
mother, it's considered a limb and the fat is not considered its
own entity and it's completely מותר muttar and that was what we
thought before. And that's the case of a קרבן. korban. A קרבן
korban is you שחט shecht the mother. So the question is why
not offer the fat on the altar? Because once you שחט shecht
the mother, we all agree that that fat is permissible. Rabbi Yochanan
was only saying his case if the mother wasn't שחט-ed shecht and
you stuck your hand up and you tore out that fat. So
it's a little strange why he has to give the answer here
like, oh, it's just not yet its right time and therefore you
don't offer. The reason you don't offer is because when you שחט
shecht the mother, it's really fully defined as a limb of the
mother. But okay, that is their debate and whether this thing that
is fully gestated but not yet born, to what degree does it
have its really its status as a
בהמה? beheimah? If you were to think about this in translate this
in human terms, something that's gestated not born, is it considered yet
to be a human? Is it considered yet to be a person?
That becomes a certainly non-trivial question. But both of these are when
it is already fully gestated. Let's take a
look. אמר רבי אמי, amar Rabbi Ami, so now says Rabbi
Ami: השוחט את הטרפה ומצא בה בן תשעה חי, hashochet et hatreifah
umatsa bah ben tisha chai, now tell the Gemara's having fun. This
is the
fast. Maybe this is part of the question whether טרפה treifa can
get pregnant and carry kids, because
maybe she became טרפה treifa after she became pregnant. Anyway, the mother's
a טרפה, treifa, you שחט shecht the mother. So it didn't make
the mother
כשר. kosher. What does it do to the fetus? Does it make
the fetus כשר? kosher? Because the fetus isn't טרפה, treifa, presumably not,
fetus is a limb of the mother, if mother's not כשר kosher
the fetus isn't כשר. kosher. Okay, what's the status of the mother?
The mother's a טרפה treifa and doesn't cause טומאה. What's the status
of the fetus? Is the fetus a טרפה? treifa? Can you שחט
shecht the fetus now? That if the fetus comes out alive, can
you שחט shecht it, or has the mother's שחיטה shechita defined its
status? So let's take a look.
So we don't have a נבלה, nevela, do
we? Because it's like that was my question before, like let's say
the mother drops dead
and there's a live fetus, then you can שחט shecht the fetus.
That was the case of the משנה.
Mishna. It's not a נבלה. nevela. Correct. So then why don't we
say the same thing here?
Because here you did a שחיטה, shechita and we normally say that
the שחיטה shechita. works for the fetus. So once we have a
principle that the שחיטה shechita works for a fetus, maybe it should
work to define its status even when it was a bad שחיטה.
shechita Not bad, but even where the שחיטה shechita of a טרפה.
treifa.
Right, right, there is a point, meaning Michael makes a good point,
when the animal dies, the death of the mother doesn't affect the
fetus, but there's no הלכה halacha about the death of the mother
changing the fetus. And that was the משנה. Mishnah, It died, you
open up the womb, and then you have a live animal, then
שחט shecht it. Then it's its own animal. But since we have
a principle that the שחיטה shechita of the mother affects the fetus,
maybe even a שחיטה shechita of a טרפה treifa affects the fetus
and it's already considered שחט-ed, shecht but not כשר, kosher, and then
you're stuck. So let's take a look. So אמר רבי אמי: Amar
Rabbi Ami: השוחט את הטרפה ומצא בה בן תשע חי. Hashochet et
hatreifa umatza bah ben tesha chai. And you found in it this
nine-month-old live fetus. לדיביה אוסר מתיר לדיביה מתיר אוסר. Lidivei oser matir
lidivei matir oser. The one who normally forbids, meaning that the שחיטה
shechita of the mother does not work for the fetus, remember רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the שחיטה shechita of the mother doesn't work for
the fetus. So fine, the שחיטה shechita was always irrelevant. Now you
have a fetus, שחט shecht the fetus, you're fine. But according to
the one who normally forbids, says the fetus doesn't work, here it
comes to your benefit. Now you can שחט shecht the fetus. But
according to the one who permits, the sages who normally say the
שחיטה shechita of the mother works for the fetus, so now you've
got a problem. The שחיטה shechita worked, but it worked in the
sense it defined the status, but it was the שחיטה shechita of
a טרפה. treifa. So you're stuck. This animal is already שחט-ed, shecht
but not כשר, kosher, and you can't שחט shecht it again.
You can't do anything.
I mean, you can't eat it. You can use it in your
field. Okay, you can sell it to a non-Jew. Right.
No, רבא אמר,
Rava amar,
רבא Rava says no, I don't think you're right, says רבא. Rava.
לדיביה דמתיר נמי מותר. Lidivei dematir nami mutar. Even according to the
sages, the שחיטה shechita of a טרפה, treifa, you can still eat
the fetus. Why? If you שחט shecht the fetus. Not the שחיטה
shechita won't do it because the mother was a טרפה, treifa, it's
not going to make the fetus כשר. kosher. But you can שחט
shecht the fetus. Why? ארבע סימנים אכשר ביה רחמנא. Arba simanim achshar
beih Rachmana.
Remember, this was an issue that came up yesterday. When we say
the שחיטה shechita of the mother works for the fetus, we're saying
it can work for the fetus, not that it's the only thing
that will allow the fetus to be eaten. And this, by the
way, plays into the idea of is the fetus really an intrinsic
part of the mother or is it connected to the mother but
not one with the mother. So if it's connected to the mother
but not one, your options are open. The שחיטה shechita. of the
mother can work for it. In this case, where the שחיטה shechita
of the mother didn't work for it because the mother was a
טרפה, treifa, it can still also have its own independent identity and
now you שחט shecht the fetus. Okay, so that's what he says.
ארבע סימנים, Arba simanim, there are which again doesn't literally mean any
two of the four, but two sets of two, you have. You
can שחט shecht the mother or שחט shecht the fetus. אמר רב
חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: השוחט את הטרפה ומצא בה בן תשע חי,
Hashochet et hatreifa umatza bah ben tesha chai,
exactly the case that we just said. You שחט-ed shecht the mother
and found a live fetus there, טעון שחיטה, teun shechita, so he
is saying it requires שחיטה. shechita It's obvious that it requires, but
the חידוש chiddush is that שחיטה shechita works. You're not stuck because
the שחיטה shechita, of the mother was, and the mother was a
טרפה. treifa. וחייב לרבא בלחיים וקיבה. Vechayav lerava belichayayim vekeiva.
And now that you שחט shecht the fetus, and you have to
שחט shecht the fetus, okay, so it's not considered שחט-ed shecht already,
then therefore when you שחט shecht it, you have to give the
proper gifts to the כהן. kohen. Because the כהן, kohen, it says
that when you שחט shecht an animal, you give the כהן, kohen,
the leg and the maw, etc. So here, right, if the שחיטה
shechita of the mother worked for the fetus, then you wouldn't have
to give those gifts to the כהן, kohen, for if you chose
to שחט shecht the fetus, it wouldn't be considered a שחיטה, shechita
it's already שחט-ed. shecht But now that the שחיטה shechita of the
mother did not work, if you're going to do a שחיטה shechita
for the fetus, it is a שחיטה shechita and you have to
do the appropriate gifts. You could also say it's אסור assur באותו
ואת בנו, be'oto ve'et beno, and so on. Okay, here's another interesting
thought question. In this case, right, what would be with the חלב
chelev and the גיד? gid? Presumably the חלב chelev and the גיד
gid would be forbidden. Once the שחיטה shechita of the mother did
not define its identity, then it's going to be its completely own
type of an animal. You can do a שחיטה shechita on it,
but it has all of the consequences of being its own animal.
ואם מת טמא ומטמא במשא. V'im meis tamei v'metamei b'masa. However,
he says there is one way the שחיטה shechita has defined it.
If this animal dies, it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Why? Because the
mother was already שחט, shechted, so that already meant that it has
the status of like a טרפה. treifa. Not as a real טרפה,
treifa, it's a little bizarre because it's its own animal and, you
know, whatever. But when it actually dies, at that stage we pay
attention to the שחיטה shechita of the mother. Here's a way of
thinking about it: The שחיטה shechita of the mother does not get
in the way. Okay, you can, you know, you can you're not
forced to define it by the שחיטה shechita of the mother. So
you can do now your own שחיטה shechita, and has all those
consequences. But the שחיטה shechita of the mother did exist and can
be relevant, and where's it relevant? When the animal is already dead
and there matters: Is it a נבלה neveilah or a טרפה? treifa?
So we'll say since the mother was a טרפה, treifa, this animal
is also a טרפה, treifa, it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, so
very yes, very, very, you know, sort
of... What? Isn't it died later? Right. Okay, אמר ליה רבא. Amar
lei Rava. So רבא Rava said to him, or some say רבה,
Rabba, because רבא Rava actually spoke earlier, so it makes sense that
this is רבה. Rabba. So רבה Rabba said to him, טעון שחיטה,
tone shechita, so you're saying it needs שחיטה, shechita, meaning and the
שחיטה shechita works, כמאן כרבי מאיר. keman ke-Rabbi Meir. So here we're
assuming not like רבא Rava said before, that's why this has to
be רבה, Rabba, that if you need שחיטה, shechita that means the
שחיטה shechita of the mother is irrelevant for it. It's not that
you have two options. So who's the one that says the שחיטה
shechita of the mother was irrelevant? That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ואם
מת טמא ומטמא במשא, V'im meis tamei v'metamei b'masa, but then you
say when it dies it's not a נבלה, neveilah, כמאן כרבנן? keman
ke-rabbanan? That's like the רבנן rabbanan who say that the שחיטה shechita
of the mother was relevant. So make up your mind. Was the
שחיטה shechita of the mother relevant or not? So he says back
to him, ואיתימא, v'ataimah, according to you, הא דתניא רבי חייא? hada
tanya Rabbi Chiya? Forget what I said. We have a ברייתא braita
that says the exact same thing I said. השוחט את הטרפה, Hashocheit
et hatreifa, word for word what he what I just said. If
you שחט shecht a טרפה, treifa,
ומצא בה בן תשע חי, u'matza bah ben tesha chai, טעון שחיטה,
tone shechita, but the mother was a טרפה, treifa, you need to
שחט shecht and you can שחט shecht the fetus. וחייב בזרוע ולחיים
ובקיבה, V'chayiv b'shroa v'lechayayim u'v'keivah,
and you give the gifts. ואם מת טמא ומטמא במשא, V'im meis
tamei v'metamei b'masa, but it's not when it dies it's not a
נבלה, neveilah, it's a טרפה. treifa. So it's exactly what he said.
So why don't you ask the same question on the ברייתא? braita?
טעון שחיטה כמאן כרבי מאיר? Tone shechita keman ke-Rabbi Meir? Saying that
it requires but also that a שחיטה shechita can work, that seems
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, because according to the רבנן rabbanan it
should be defined by the שחיטה shechita of the mother and be
a טרפה treifa end of story. So that's saying a שחיטה shechita
can work means it's its own entity, it's like רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. ואם מת טמא ומטמא במשא, V'im meis tamei v'metamei b'masa, but
if it dies it's considered to be not a נבלה, neveilah, the
שחיטה shechita defined it already and it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Who's
that? כרבנן? Ke-rabbanan? Like the רבנן. rabbanan. So why don't... basically he's
saying we have a ברייתא braita that says word for word what
I said. Of course תוספות says then why did you say it?
Why didn't you just quote the ברייתא? braita? Okay, but whatever the
answer to that is, it's actually quite fascinating in the בבלי, Bavli,
you know scholars have pointed it out that there are sometimes אמוראיק
amoraic statements and then it says, you know, אמר רב יהודה amar
Rav Yehuda or whatever, A, B, C, D, E. תניא נמי הכי,
Tanya nami hachi, A, B, C, D, E. Like a ברייתא braita
is word for word for an אמוראיק amoraic statement. So what exactly
is happening there? Anyways, תוספות asks that here. But be that as
it may, then why challenge me? I just said the same thing
a ברייתא braita said. And here it says that on one hand
it says the שחיטה shechita did not define it because you can
do even though the mother was a טרפה treifa you can שחט
shecht the fetus, and on the other hand it says the שחיטה
shechita did define it and if it dies it's a טרפה treifa
and it's not a נבלה. neveilah. So obviously what we're leading up
to is the position of רבא, Rava, which is that you can
choose whether the שחיטה shechita of the mother defines it or not.
You're not limited by the שחיטה shechita of the mother. Okay, but
that's what he said back. Why not ask this to a ברייתא?
braita? So אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he says, one minute, הא לא קשיא. ha lo kashya.
That's not difficult why he didn't ask it on a ברייתא. braita.
Why? רבי חייא אם כבר מצאו מת קאמר. Rabbi Chiya im kevar
matzo meis ka'amar.
When it says if it dies it's a טרפה treifa not a
נבלה, neveilah, he didn't mean this fetus was alive and grew up
and then it died. I would have understood the ברייתא braita to
mean that if you שחט shechted the mother and the mother was
a טרפה treifa and the fetus was already dead in the mother's
womb, then the fetus is also a טרפה. treifa. Not that it
lived and died later. Okay, that's how I would have interpreted the
ברייתא braita and then it wouldn't have been a problem. It would
have basically been saying that the שחיטה shechita of the mother is,
you know, irrelevant for the fetus, but if... but
but if the fetus was alive, but when the fetus was dead
then it is relevant. אלא לדידך, Ella l'didach,
but according to you, you could have given me that answer and
you didn't give me that answer. So קשיא. kashya. Clearly you mean
this literally. Since you didn't give me that answer and you literally
mean the fetus was alive and walking around and then died and
it's not a נבלה. neveilah. So that sounds like the שחיטה shechita?
of the mother was relevant. If the שחיטה shechita of the mother
was relevant, then if the mother was a טרפה, treifa, how can
you now eat the fetus? how can you do its own שחיטה?
shechita So אמר ליה amar lei and now it's what we said
before, לדידי נמי לא קשיא, l'didi nami lo kashya, I don't have
a problem, that's exactly the point. ארבעה סימנים אכשר בה רחמנא. Arba
simanim achshar bei rachmana.
The Torah gives four סימנים. simanim. The שחיטה shechitah of the mother
is not the only thing that can define the fetus. It can,
but not must define the fetus. So if the mother is kosher,
the שחיטה shechitah of the mother means the fetus is already שחט.
shechted. If the mother however is טרפה... treifa... If the mother, however,
is טרפה, treifah, then the שחיטה shechitah of the mother is irrelevant,
or doesn't have to be relevant. Maybe it'll play a role when
the fetus dies, but it doesn't have to be relevant, you can
treat it on its own terms and you can do a שחיטה
shechitah on the fetus now and eat the fetus. Yes.
In terms ארבעה סימנים arba simanim implies that you might have be
able to eat the fetus after שחט shechting one pipe of the
mother and one pipe.
I mentioned that the other day. It's, you know, it's like a
very, it's like a powerful phrase, it's a nice concise way of
saying, you know, like sort of, you know, that you can use
the mother's שחיטה shechitah but you don't have to. ארבעה סימנים arba
simanim it's you know, it's sort of, you know, we tend to
remember things that are, you know, these are like memory tricks, right?
You know, things that are more bizarre and create strange images in
our head. I will bet you that a month from now you're
not going to forget the idea that we said that this fetus
has four סימנים. simanim. You know, right? That's like so it's a
very concise way of saying it in a way that you'll remember
it, but it's not, you know, it's not precise. Okay, because you're
correct. It really means two sets of סימנים. simanim. It doesn't mean
any two out of the four. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. כי סליק רבי זירא Ki salik Rabbi Zeira when
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה
לרבי אסי, ashkachei le-Rabbi Assi,
he found רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, דיתיב וקאמר לה להא שמעתא, de-yasiv
ve-ka-mar leh le-hai shamaita, he was telling over this idea that if
the mother was a טרפה, treifah, you're not limited by the שחיטה
shechitah. of the mother and you can שחט shecht the fetus and
eat the fetus. אמר ליה Amar leh so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said to רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, יישר, Yee ashar, like you know,
יישר כח, Yasher koach, right? So you know now people say that,
I find that that's a little bit you know be nicer to
say like thank you or good job. יישר כח Yasher koach is
a little but what okay. Anyway they said it already then. יישר
כח, Yasher koach, good, yeah, you're right. That's a good פשט. pshat.
וכן אמר רבי יוחנן. Ve-chen amar Rabbi Yochanan. And that's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says too, that even if the mother was a
טרפה treifah and you שחט shecht the mother, you can still שחט
shecht the fetus. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דפליג ליה ריש
לקיש? mikhlelad de-palig leh Resh Lakish? So you know it's so funny.
Since you said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it, well what about
ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? We always hear what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
holds, and why didn't you say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. and ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says it? So the fact that you didn't mention
ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish position, does this mean to suggest that ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish disagrees? So says the גמרא, Gemara no, משא הוה
שהי ליה ושתיק ליה. mesha havah shehi leh ve-shatik leh. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish was being quiet and didn't respond and I never got
to hear, you know, he didn't respond immediately and I never got
to hear what what ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish opinion was. Maybe he
agreed, maybe he disagreed, I left before I got to hear what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish was saying. רש"י says that actually ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish would wait a would have a practice of waiting before
voicing any disagreement with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan Now if somebody said
that to you, you'd say why would you wait? Because you want
to make sure that you're really certain about your reasons for disagreeing
and you know, and think it through and maybe you'll wind up
realizing that the other person was right. רש"י says ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish would wait because he was going to see whether רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan would reverse himself or not before he would disagree. So
that's anyway they said it already. But either way he said I
don't know what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said. He didn't mention ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish not because he disagrees because I left before I
heard a response. Maybe he was going to disagree and he was
just waiting, maybe not. איכא דאמרי, Ikka de-amri, others say, משתי הוה
שתי ליה ושתיק ליה. mishtei havah sheti leh ve-shatik leh. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish was in the middle of drinking when רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said this. He was in the middle of his meal, so
he couldn't interrupt to be and I don't know what ריש לקיש's
Resh Lakish opinion was. He could have said maybe he was sick
that day. Okay, but anyway, I know what רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan,
opinion was, I don't know what ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish opinion was.
All right, so with that we have the opinions of שחיטה shechitah
of the mother working for the fetus, a fully gestated fetus in
the mother's womb before it's born, what's that status? And again this
interesting question of if the mother's a טרפה, treifah, do you still
have the option of שחט shechting the fetus and treating it like
its own thing? ארבעה סימנים אחשביה רחמנא Arba Simanim Achshvei Rachmana or
not? Now we go to the second statement in the משנה, Mishna,
the very graphic statement of even if the animal was five years
old and plowing in the field, you still don't need a שחיטה.
shechitah So let's take a look. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר אפילו Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri omer afilu even if the animal was, you know, five
years five years old, you know, it grew up and it's plowing
the fields, the שחיטה shechitah of the mother still works for it.
היינו תנא קמא, Heinu Tanna Kamma, isn't that exactly the first opinion,
that the שחיטה shechitah, of the mother works for it? So אמר
רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, הפיס על גבי קרקע איכא בינייהו. hiphis
agabi karka ikka beinyahu. It's a difference about whether from the word
פרסה parsah hoofs, whether its hoofs have laid down on the ground.
What does this mean? So now, after using reading these amazing גמרות
Gemoras about how the שחיטה shechitah. of the mother works for the
fetus and you can eat it and all those things and we
want to have farms of raising בן פקועה ben pakuas that don't
need שחיטה, shechitah. now we're going to find out that there's a
little rabbinic problem at least according to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
There'll be a question how we פוסקים, pasken, which is, you know,
it doesn't look so good to eat an animal without שחיטה. shechitah
So now we're going to say that that's exactly where רבי שמעון
שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says even if the animal's walking around, whatever,
I don't care what it looks like, you can eat it without
שחיטה. shechitah? So what does that suggest to the תנא קמא? Tanna
Kamma? It suggests that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma doesn't want you
in that case, even if technically you can, to eat without שחיטה
shechitah because it doesn't look right. So when can you eat without
שחיטה? shechita, If it never actually stood up and started walking around.
So there was the fetus, it was alive, you
killed
it on the spot, then you can eat. But if it actually
got up and walked around and started looking not like a piece
of meat, but started looking like an animal, at that stage at
least rabbinically you would have to שחט shecht it. So there's a
debate of רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and the חכמים, Chachamim,
do we have a rabbinic concern of requiring שחיטה shechita even when
the you know, after the animal is walking around? up and walking
around. In the end, I'll just ruin the surprise for you, we
rule like the חכמים, Chachamim, which means that the whole בן פקועה
Ben Pekua farm is a little bit to have to put- you
have to- you have to- you have to- you have to put
in the back burner; except there still is a benefit because even
if you need שחיטה, shechita we're going to see that you can
still eat the חלב chelev and you still don't have to worry
about the גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. And you don't have to worry
if it's a טריפה. treifa, So it's whole- just a מראית עין
maris ayin issue. So you can't have an animal walking around that
you don't do שחיטה shechita? to, but you can do שחיטה shechita
and you don't have to worry about טריפה, treifa and you don't
have to worry about חלב, chelev, and you don't have to worry
about גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. So there still is money to be
made in this בן פקועה Ben Pekua farm, see? So we're explaining
young? Exactly. Okay, but what about the חלב chalav though?
Does it look good either to be cooking it with meat, but
you can.
Oh, that's an interesting question.
Let's see thing, do we?
No, but this is- what do you mean? This is not פרווה.
parve. I don't know where you got that idea. This is a
limb of the mother and it's meat. It's totally meat.
Wait, I'm sorry, meaning no,
but- no, you're talking about חלב שחוטה. chalav shechuta. Yeah. The חלב
chalav in the- the milk in the udder. That's not our discussion.
Yeah, but let's say you wanted to cook it with meat, right?
Wouldn't look good cooking your- I don't understand.
This בן פקועה Ben Pekua is meat. It's פלייש. flesh. You're confusing
it with a case about milk found in the udder, which is
not our case right now.
No, but let's just think it through. Take- do a ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. Yes.
Yes,
doesn't this prove that cruelty to animals has nothing to do with
שחיטה? shechita.
It's dissociated because- Why?
Because if you can kill an animal, maybe you kill it- right.
Then- then cruelty- we're not
concerned- maybe, maybe you do it without inflicting pain. All it means
is that that's not the only way to kill an animal without,
you know- maybe it means that we don't care if the animal
suffers in the process, or maybe it means that there are alternative
ways to do it without suffering. We're not, you know, we're just
saying that שחיטה shechita doesn't have to be the only- doesn't have
to be שחיטה.
shechita But we always say שחיטה shechita is the most painless.
I understand. Look, we've seen that throughout, that there's not really a
discourse in the גמרא Gemara about צער בעלי חיים tzaar baalei chayim
and all these discussions. Okay, let's keep on going. So the גמרא
says, אמר רב משרישא לדידי אמר חוששין לזרע האב, Amar Rav Mesharshaya
ledidi amar chosheshin lezera ha'av, according to the opinion that we're concerned
about who the father is, which A means that we have to
by animals think we know who the father is, and B means
who the father is has הלכה halakhic implications for the child. So
according to that opinion, בן פקועה הבא על בהמה מעליאתא הולד אין
לו תקנה. Ben Pekua haba al behema mealyata havlad ein lo takana.
If a male בן פקועה Ben Pekua has intercourse with a female
cow that's not a בן פקועה, Ben Pekua, then the child, which
is half of a- half בן פקועה, Ben Pekua, its parentage is
half בן פקועה Ben Pekua half normal, so there's no way to
שחט shecht it. Why? Because the שחיטה shechita of the mother already
defined the בן פקועה. Ben Pekua. Okay? In a case where the
שחיטה shechita of the mother worked, you don't have another option. When
we discussed other options it was when the שחיטה shechita of the
mother didn't work or didn't occur yet. But here the שחיטה shechita
of the mother worked. So from that perspective, this animal's שחיטה shechita
is irrelevant. From the perspective of the mother, שחיטה shechita is relevant
and required. So you can't not do a שחיטה shechita. because of
the perspective of the mother. You can't do a שחיטה shechita, and
say you were יוצא yotzei because it was a meaningless act from
the- from the half of it that says that it's already שחט.
shecht. So this animal you are stuck with. Okay. I mean here,
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, I have no idea, it's a good point.
It really doesn't belong because now we're going to get back to
the רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. I don't know what it
was doing yet. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הכל מודים בקלוט בן פקועה.
Hakol modim bekalut Ben Pekua. Now we're going back to the concern
about the מראית עין maris ayin about שחט shechting an animal that's
been walking around. So אביי Abaye says there's some exception. Since it's
a concern about people won't remember and it'll look like it was
a normal animal, if the animal was born with a weird birth
defect and people will remember it- so for example, the case the
גמרא talks about- talks about is where the hooves were combined and
not split, that was your בן פקועה. Ben Pekua. He says then
even the rabbis would say you could שחט shecht it years later.
Why? Because everybody will remember, "Oh yeah, of course, that's not a
normal animal, that was their bizarre בן פקועה Ben Pekua Ben Pekua
that came out with that birth defect."
Yeah, just some mutated animal.
So if that's true, right, okay, שמותר, shemutar. that is permissible. מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? כל מילתא דתמיה מדכרי לה אינשי.
Kol milta detmiha midkeri lei inshi.
Anything that's astounding is like we said before about remembering bizarre things,
people will remember. So they'll see that it's non-split hoof, they'll also
remember that it's that animal that was the בן פקועה Ben Pakua,
and they won't be astounded that you're not doing
שחיטה. shechita איכא דאמרי, Ikka d'amri, some say, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
that אביי Abaye said, הכל מודים בקלוט בן קלוטה בן פקועה שמותר,
Hakol modim bekalut ben keluta Ben Pekua shemutar, that it's only if
it has a double bizarre thing going on. Okay? It is a-
the mother itself had non-split hooves and the fetus was non-split hooves.
In that case, then it was so bizarre that everybody will remember
that. Okay. שמותר. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? תרתי תמיהי מדכרי אינשי. Tartei tmihei midkeri inshi. People remember two
things that are astounding, but they won't necessarily remember one thing that
is
astounding. One minute.
It has to be the same thing for the mother and-
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, no, רש״י Rashi says, I misread the גמרא
a little bit, it's not the mother- a normal mother was a
קלוטה, keluta, it's- it's even more bizarre. The קלוט... kalut... קלוטה, Klutah,
the first there was a בן פקועה, Ben Pakua, it was a
קלוטה, Klutah, and then it had a child, and then it had
a בן פקועה, Ben Pakua and that בן פקועה Ben Pakua, was
a קלוטה. Klutah. Okay? So there's two right, it's repeated for two
generations that you had a קלוטה Klutah that was a בן פקועה,
Ben Pakua. and then that you right you opened up the womb,
you saw a fetus with unslit hooves, that animal grew up, had
a child, you שחט shachted the mother, and the child was a
בן פקועה. Ben Pakua What? Had another בן פקועה Ben Pakua.
and that was also the other the the mated with a בן
פקועה. Ben Pakua, What? It had to mate with a בן פקועה,
Ben Pakua, right?
No, not in order no, if the fetus itself was a בן
פקועה, Ben Pakua, that's sufficient by the גמרא we
just read that was split...
yeah, but that was okay I can't go into it now. But
the answer is no. Anyway, the point is that if you had
this whole double thing, it happened the exact same thing happened for
two generations, not split hooves and בן פקועה, Ben Pakua, that people
remember. Okay, I want to just read one more line because this
is interesting, important to the כשרות Kashrut issue and concerns the טריפה
treifa. issue. So let's just read this. אמר זירא אמר רב חנינא
הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי. Amar Zeira amar Rav Chanina halacha k'Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri. We rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, we don't
worry about מראית עין. marit ayin. Even if it's walking around and
healthy, you can שחט shacht it. וכן היה רבי שמעון שזורי מתיר
בבנו ובן בנו עד סוף כל הדורות. V'chein haya Rabbi Shimon Shezuri
matir bivno u'ven bno ad sof kol hadorot. Not only that, not
only the בן פקועה, Ben Pakua. but even multiple generations of the
בן פקועה. Ben Pakua Again, whether it matters who the father was
or not, we could discuss, but even if it's multiple generations, so
it could be a hundred years later, here's our בן פקועה Ben
Pakua. farm, a hundred years from the original בן פקועה. Ben Pakua,
It certainly you would think it's a מראית עין. marit ayin. Nobody's
going to remember. I don't care. It's a בן פקועה, Ben Pakua.
go ahead and eat it without שחיטה, shechita, or it's a descendant
of בן פקועה. Ben Pakua רבי יוחנן אומר הוא מותר, Rabbi Yochanan
omer hu mutar, he's going to split his vote. The original בן
פקועה Ben Pakua, is okay, ובנו אסור, u'bno assur, not the child.
Although the child הלכתית halachically is a בן פקועה, Ben Pakua, that
makes sense, right? Although the child הלכתית halachically is a בן פקועה,
Ben Pakua. by the second generation, nobody is going to remember and
there's a serious מראית עין marit ayin concern, there's a serious מכשול
michshol concern, but the first generation, there you can rule the extra
ruling. Let me just rule one more thing and then I'll take
a question. אדא בר חבו הוה ליה בן פקועה. Ada bar Chavu
hava lei ben pakua. So אדא בר חבו Ada bar Chavu had
this בן פקועה. Ben Pakua דנפל דובא עליה, D'nafal duba aleih, a
wolf
attacked it and made it a טריפה. treifa. Okay, אתא לקמיה דרב
אשי, Ata l'kamei d'Rav Ashi, he came to רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
אמר ליה זיל שחטיה או שחטיה. Amar lei zil shachtia o shachtia.
Okay, because א, alef, you require שחיטה shechita, like the רבנן, Rabbanan,
we're going to rule like the רבנן Rabbanan that you require שחיטה,
shechita? but it's because it's only for appearances' sake, you only have
to worry about שחיטה, shechita, you don't have to worry about טריפה.
treifa. אמר ליה הא מר זירא אמר רב חנינא הלכה כרבי שמעון
שזורי. Amar lei ha mar Zeira amar Rav Chanina halacha k'Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri. His only issue was, why do I even need to do
שחיטה? shechita Don't we say, don't these רבנים Rabbanim say we rule
like רבי שמעון שזורי? Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? וכן היה רבי שמעון שזורי
מתיר בבנו ובן בנו עד סוף כל הדורות. V'chein haya Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri matir bivno u'ven bno ad sof kol hadorot. And he some
say he would allow multiple generations, ואפילו רבי יוחנן לא קאמר אלא
בבנו. V'afilu Rabbi Yochanan lo q'amar ela bivno. And even רבי יוחנן,
he says okay the later generations you need שחיטה, shechita. איהו לא,
ihu lo, but but the actual בן פקועה Ben Pakua he rules
at least rules that that you don't need שחיטה shechita for, we
don't we're not concerned of appearances. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
says, רבי יוחנן לדברי רבי שמעון שזורי קאמר. Rabbi Yochanan l'divrei Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri q'amar. He was saying according to רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri, but he wasn't ruling like רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri. And we actually rule like the חכמים Chachamim that you need
שחיטה. shechita, So he says, one minute, ואמר רבין בר חנינא אמר
עולא אמר רבי חנינא הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי? V'amar Ravin bar Chanina
amar Ulla amar Rabbi Chanina halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? But don't we
say we rule like רבי שמעון שזורי? Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? ולא עוד
אלא כל מקום ששנה רבי שמעון שזורי במשנתנו הלכה כמותו. V'lo od
ela kol makom she'shana Rabbi Shimon Shezuri b'mishnateinu halacha k'moto. There's a
general principle that whenever רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri appears in
a משנה, we rule like him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said,
אנא כי האי סבירא לי. Ana ki hai sevira li. I hold
like a different opinion about רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. דאמר
רבי יונתן הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי במסוכן ובתרומת מעשר של דמאי. D'amar
Rabbi Yonatan halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri b'mesukan u'vitrumat ma'aser shel demai. And
we'll have to end here, unfortunately, we we should have really got
to the end of the page, but it's already late. But he
basically says we only rule like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri
in two cases, we'll find out what those two cases are tomorrow,
but they're not really relevant for our concerns. And the real point
is we don't rule like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and
we rule like the חכמים. Chachamim. And you take a look, the
רמב"ם Rambam and שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch both say, they although so
many people here ruled like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, since
it ends with this case, we rule like the חכמים Chachamim that
once it walks around, you still are going to require שחיטה shechita,
for appearances, but because it's just appearances, like the case said, it
doesn't matter if the animal is טריפה. treifa Okay, if you kill
an animal without שחיטה, that gets people wondering, but nobody really knows
טריפה treifa, issues, that happens in, you know, that's not a public
thing. And therefore that is not a concern, so at least the
benefit of a בן פקועה farm is not that it eliminates שחיטה,
but it eliminates concerns about טריפה, חלב, chelev, and גיד הנשה. gid
hanasheh. All right.